Guide to the Theodore Enslin Papers ca. 1955-1975 MSS.047
Fales Library and Special Collections
Theodore Enslin Papers
ca. 1955-1975
Fales Library and Special Collections
Enslin, Theodore
MSS.047
3.5 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
Scope and Content note
The Theodore Enslin Papers are a collection of correspondence and manuscripts written to and by Theodore Enslin between 1957 and 1975. Collection highlights include letters written by Paul Blackburn, Robert Bly, Carol Berge, Hayden Carruth, Cid Corman, Diane DiPrima, Clayton Eshleman, Ian Hamilton Finlay, Henry Rago and Gary Snyder.
SERIES DESCRIPTION:
Series I: Correspondence
Series I contains five boxes of correspondence with such notable literary figures as Paul Blackburn, Robert Bly, Hayden Carruth, Cid Corman, Diane DiPrima, Denise Levertov, Gary Snyder and Theodore Weiss.
Series II: Manuscripts
Series II contains two boxes of manuscripts by Theodore Enslin, including Forms I-IV and miscellanous poems and prose.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Arrangement note
The Theodore Enslin Papers are arranged in alphabetical and chronological order.
Missing Title
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Manuscripts
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Theodore Enslin Papers were purchased from Theodore Enslin between 1968-1975.
Biographical/Historical note
Theodore Enslin was born in Chester, PA on March 25, 1925. He studied muscial composition with Nadia Boulanger and Francis Judd Cooke. He has two children, Deirdre and Jonathan Morton, from his first marriage with Mildred Marie Stout in 1945. He divorced in 1961 and married Alison Jane Jose in 1969, with whom he had a son, Jacob Hezakiah. Theodore Enslin has written many books of poetry, including Forms (1971-73), The Poems (1970), Views (1973), Synthesis (1975), Etudes (1972) and To Come, to Have Become (1966) for which he won the Hart Crane Award in 1969. Other awards include the Niemann Award in 1955 for his weekly newspaper column, "Six Miles Square." Enslin has also written a play, Barometric Pressure 29.83 and Steady (produced in New York in 1965), and an extended essay on Gustav Mahler published by Black Sparrow Press.
Scripts (documents); Correspondence.; American poetry |y 20th century |v Periodicals.; Avant-garde poetry.; Avant-garde literature.; Proofs (printed matter); American poetry |y 20th century.; American literature |y 20th century.; Snyder, Gary, 1930-; Eshleman, Clayton; Levertov, Denise, 1923-1997; Carruth, Hayden, 1921-2008; Blackburn, Paul; Lewis, Harry; Randall, Margaret, 1936-; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972; Corman, Cid; Bergé, Carol, 1928-; Kelly, Robert, 1935-; Bly, Robert; Taggart, John, 1942-; Wieners, John, 1934-2002; Wakoski, Diane
- Series I: Correspondence
  - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Abrams, Samuel
    Aldan, Daisy
    Allen, Donald
    Anastas, Peter
    Anderson, Lee
    Antin, David
    Antin, Eleanor
    Ashman, Richard
  - Arnett, Carroll, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - B, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Beltrametti, Franco
    Beum, Robert
    Bealy, Harvey
    Boulanger, Nasha
    Braun, Henry
    Bronk, William
    Brown, William
    Brubeck, Dave
    Butterick, George
  - Banks, Russell, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Blackburn, Paul, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bly, Robert, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Berge, Carol, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bowering, George, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - C, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Calhoun, Douglas
    Carroll, Paul
    Childs, Barry
    Chute, Robert
    Coleman, Victor
    Coupland, Ken
    Curry, David
  - Cabassa, Stella Leonardas, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    see also legal size folder "Enslin"
    (Cabassa is T. E.'s translator in Portuguese)
  - Carruth, Hayden, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Corman, Cid, 1964-1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - D, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Dean, Nicholas
    DeLoach, Allen
    Dennison, George
    DiPrima, Diane
    Doyle, Michael
    Durrett, Eustace
  - E, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Eberhart, Richard
    Emerson, R. W.
    Evans, Paul
  - Eshleman, Clayton, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    (see also legal folder)
  - F, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Fowler, Albert
    Frank, David
    Finlay, Ian Hamilton (see also legal folder)
  - G, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Gerber, Daniel
    Gitin, David
    Glover, Albert
    Greenberg, Al (1962-1968)
    Griffin, John Howard
    Griffith, E.
  - Goodman, Mitchell (re: Denise Levertov), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Geyerhahn, Gordon, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Greene, Jonathan, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Grieder, Ted [NYU], undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Grossinger, Richard, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - H, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Hamady, Walter
    Hanna, Charles
    Hanson, Ken
    Hay, John
    Haydn, Hiram
    Higgins, Dick
    Hirschman, Jack
    Hoffman, Daniel
    Hough, Lindy (Grossinger)
    Hopper, Jack
  - Harris, Marie, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Holsapple, Bruce, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - I, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Ignatof, David
    Irby, Kenneth
  - J, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Johnson, Ronald
    Jones, Jeanetta
  - Johnston, George, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    (see also Legal Folders)
  - K, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Kiralis, Karl
    Kizer, Carolyn
    Koller, James
    Krey, Elizabeth
  - Kelly, Robert, 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Kelly, Robert, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - King, Basil [Martha], 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - L, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Larson, Carl
    Laughlin, James
    Layton, Irving
    Levendosky, Charles
    Linick, Anthony
  - to La Belle, Christine, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - to La Belle, Christine, Jan.-Jun. 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - to La Belle, Christine, Jul.-Dec. 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - to La Belle, Christine, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - to La Belle, Christine, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - to La Belle, Christine, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Levertov, Denise, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    (see Mitchell Goodman)
  - Lewis, Harry, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    {see also Legal Folders)
  - Lewis, Harry, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - to Lewis, Harry, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Lish, Gordon, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - M, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Marlatt, Daphne
    Metzer, David
    Moraff, Barbara
    Morris, Richard
    Morris, Robert
    Mottram, Eric
  - McCord, Howard, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - McCord, Howard, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Martell, Charles, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Marton, John [Black Sparrow], undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Merton, Thomas, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Metcalf, Paul, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Metzger, Wendell, 1966-1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Moore, Marianne, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - N-O, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Newberry, Samuel
    Olson, Toby
    Ossman, David
  - Oppen, George, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - P, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Perchik, Simon
    Perkoff, Stuart
    Phelps, Donald
  - R, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Rago, Henry
    Reznikoff, Charles
    Rothenberg, Jerome
  - Randall, Margaret [El Corneo Emplumado], undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Reyes, Carlos, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Rowan, Louis, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - S, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Samperi, Frank
    Schreiber, Ron
    Schwerner, Armand
    Shahoud, Charles
    Solotaroff, Theodore
    Stefanile, Felix
    Stock, Noel
  - Salstrom, Paul, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sherman, Susan, 1962-1974 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Shoemaker, Jack, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Silliman, Ronald, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Snyder, Gary, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Souster, Raymond H., undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - T, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Thayler, Carl
    Thurman, Eva
    Tolstoy, Ivan
    Turnbull, Gael
  - Taggart, John, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Taggart, John, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Taggart, John, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - to Taggart, John, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - to Taggart, John, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - to Taggart, John, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - V, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Valkenier, Willem A.
    Varese, Louise
    Van Dias, Robert
  - W, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Wade, John Stevens
    Webb, Jon
    Williams, Loring
    Williams, Paul
  - Wakowski, Diane, 1962-1974 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Weil, James, 1963-1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Weil, James, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - to Weil, James, 1963-1966 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - to Weil, James, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - to Weil, James, 1970-1973, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Weiss, Theodore; Whitney, John D., undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Wieners, John, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Williams, Jonathan, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Wilson, Keith, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Wroth, Will [William], undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Zukofsky, Louis, 1958-1971 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Series II: Manuscripts
  - Forms I - printers copy, p. 1-100, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    [see also Galleys]
  - Forms I - printers copy, p. 101-198, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Forms I - page proofs, 112 pgs., undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Forms II [The Tessaract] - printers copy, p. 183-265, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Forms II [The Tessaract] - p. 266-351, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Forms III - typescript of LXXIV-LXXV, p. 83 of printers copy, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Forms III - printers copy, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Forms III.2 - printers copy, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Forms IV - typescript XCVIII-XCVIX, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Forms IV.1 - printers copy, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Forms IV.2 - printers copy, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Misc. A-L, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    "The Belongings." Ms. (12 April 1962)
    Etudes. Ms.
    Etudes. Ts. 41p. (1972)
    "Fascicles." Ms.
    "The Log." Ms.
  - Misc. N-P, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    "A New Morality & Its Generation"
    "Notes from a Line to a Line"
    "Philo Logos"
    "The Place Poem"
  - The Poems - Ms. (1966-1967); Ts. (1970), 1966-1967, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - The Poems - Page proofs, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Poems and prose, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Some Roads Around Olson's (s.a. Synthesis 18); "Sweet Hour of Prayer", undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Synthesis; short poems; "Night Shower", undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Times of Day (One to Another?), undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Views, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Work in progress, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)